Diocesan Labor Institute Records 1984.0030
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Diocesan Labor Institute Records
undated, 1944-1973
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0030
4 Linear Feet
The Diocesan Labor Institute was founded in 1942 by Joseph F. Donnelly, then a Waterbury parish priest, later a monsignor, and eventually Auxiliary Bishop of the Hartford Archdiocese. The main purpose of Institute was to instruct workers on Catholic social philosophy and on the basics of trade unionism.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The records of the Diocesan Labor Institute were deposited with the Connecticut Labor Archives in May 1984.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence (1944-1964) contains chronologically arranged files of letters and memoranda both to and from the Diocesan Labor Institute and Father Joseph Donnelly, director. This series also includes notes from meetings of the Directors of the Labor Institute as well as personal notes from Father Donnelly.
Series II: Minutes (1948-1957) consists of minutes from the meetings of the Directors of the Diocesan Labor Institute of Hartford. The minutes contain information on such topics as attendance, regulations of the formal programs, the McAullife Medal Award, and Social Action Sunday. This series is arranged in chronological order.
Series III: Reports (undated, 1944-1956) contains chronologically arranged Institute Reports written by Father Donnelly and submitted to Henry O'Brien, Monthly Chapter Reports, and Survey Reports. Institute Reports cover such topics as the work of the Institute, activities of the Institute, activities of the local chapters, and the future of the Diocesan Labor Institute. Also included are brief overviews of the programs and activities of the Institute.
Monthly Chapter Reports, arranged alphabetically by Connecticut chapter, consists of files of monthly reports on the activities of chapters and items of information from Comment for the Priest's Bulletin from 1945-1948.
Survey Reports holds chronologically arranged files concerning a labor survey performed by the Institute. Topics included in the survey are employee/employer relationships, work ethics, and working conditions.
Series IV: Subject Files (undated, 1949-1964) holds alphabetically arranged files on a variety of subjects, including such topics as Conference of Christians and Jews, Labour School, Milk Strike, and Social Action Sunday.
Series V: Publications (undated, 1946-1973) are files of various publications with which the Diocesan Labor Institute was involved. These publications include Social Action Bulletin and Labour School.
Series VI: Photographs (undated) consists of one folder of photographs of various Diocesan Labor Institute lecturers.
History
The Diocesan Labor Institute was founded in 1942 by Joseph F. Donnelly, then a Waterbury parish priest, later a monsignor, and eventually Auxiliary Bishop of the Hartford Archdiocese. The main purpose of Institute was to instruct workers on Catholic social philosophy and on the basics of trade unionism. In addition, chapter directors attempted to persuade businessmen to cooperate with organized labor and they counseled workers fighting to oust Communist union leaders. In the early years, the Institute enjoyed much success. By the early 1950s, however, participation dropped significantly because many union officials were already graduates of the Institute. In an attempt to give new life to the Institute, a survey was introduced to communicate Catholic ideas about economic life to trade unionists.
The survey failed to revive the movement, but it produced a unique source for historians, as it offers vivid descriptions of working-life and reveals a great deal about the worldview of the priests who worked with unions. The survey involved gathering contacts in the local labor movement for a series of weekly evening discussions on the problems and attitudes of workers. The results were reported to Monsignor Donnelly in monthly chapter reports. Between autumn 1954 and spring 1956, the Diocesan Labor Institute of Connecticut held 150 meetings with small groups of Catholic trade unionists.
Scope and Content
The Diocesan Labor Institute Records contain office files, including correspondence, reports, publications and similar materials, from the Catholic labor movement and survey reports from 1944-1964.
Connecticut (state); Correspondence; Labor unions; Catholic labor unions; Administrative records; Photographs; Publications (documents)
- Series I: Correspondence, 1944-1964
  - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1953 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1954 January - March (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1954 June - December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1955 January - March (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1955 April - June (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1955 July - September (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1955 October - December (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1956 January - March (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1956 April - June (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1956 July - December (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1957 January - March (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1957 April - June (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1957 July - December (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1958 January - June (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1961 July - 1962 June (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1963 June - 1964 June (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Series II: Minutes, 1948 - 1957
  - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - 1949 September (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1950 September (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1951 January (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1951 September (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1952 January (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 1952 September 30 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 1953 February 3 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - 1953 September (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - 1954 February 17 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 1954 September (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - 1955 May (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - 1955 October (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - 1956 May (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 1956 September (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - 1956 September (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - 1956 October (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - 1957 November (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Series III: Reports, undated, 1944 - 1956
  - Institute Reports
    - 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 1951 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 1952 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - 1953 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Monthly Chapter Reports
    - General, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - General, 1950 November - December (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - General, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Ansonia, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Bridgeport, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Bristol, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Danbury, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Hartford, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Manchester, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Meriden, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Middletown, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - New Britain, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - New Haven, undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - New London, undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Norwalk, undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Stamford, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Torrington, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Waterbury, undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Willimantic, undated (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - General, 1954 June (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Survey Reports
    - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 85)
- Series IV: Subject Files, undated, 1949 - 1964
  - Catholic University, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - C. P. I., 1962 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Complimentary, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Conference of Christians and Jews, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), undated (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence, unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Donations and Records Essay Contest, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Donations, Institute, undated (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Essay contest, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 94-98)
  - Executive Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Fair Employee Practices, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Forums - Waterbury, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 101-102)
  - Human relations, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Human Relations in Modern Business, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Human Relations Advisor, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Institute Reform, undated (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Invocation: replies, undated (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Labour School, undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Labour School notes, 1945-1955 (Box 3, Folder 109-116)
  - Labour School - Group Discussion, undated (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - McAuliffe Medal, 1949-1964 (Box 3, Folder 118-140)
  - Milk Strike, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Minimum Wage Director, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 142)
  - National Catholic Social Action Conference, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - National Catholic Social Action Conference, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - National Catholic Social Action Conference, 1956-1962 (Box 4, Folder 145-146)
  - Bishop O'Brien, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - ACTU Basic Training Course, undated (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - New Brunswick Discussion, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - New Haven District of the Diocesan Bureau of Social Services, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Personal correspondence, 1945-1955 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Priests Conference, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Priests Study Group, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Problems and policies, undated (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Public speaking: Labour School, undated (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - Reneault, 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 156)
  - Bishops Sheehan and Flanagan: correspondence, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 157)
  - Social Action Bulletin, 1949-1957 (Box 4, Folder 158)
  - Social Action correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 159)
  - Social Action Institute: Washington, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 160)
  - First Labour School notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 161)
  - Social Action Sunday, 1951-1963 (Box 4, Folder 162-174)
  - Social Action Sunday, Bishop Flanagan: Bishop of Norwalk, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 175)
  - Social Action Sunday, Bishop Sheehan: Bishop of Bridgeport, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 176)
  - Social Action Sunday: newspaper clippings, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 177)
  - Social Action Sunday: sermon notes, 1951-1961 (Box 4, Folder 178)
  - Subscription lists, undated (Box 4, Folder 179)
  - The Cauldron, 1949-1964 (Box 4, Folder 180-186)
  - Union Rights and Duties, undated (Box 4, Folder 187)
- Series V: Publications, undated, 1946-1955
  - Social Action Bulletin, 1946-1951 (Box 4, Folder 188)
  - The Challenge of the Church, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 189)
  - Street `n Steeple: General Board of Evangelism, undated (Box 4, Folder 190)
  - Connecticut Labour Department Monthly Bulletin, 1955 December (Box 4, Folder 191)
  - Labour School, undated (Box 4, Folder 192-193)
  - Mater et Magistra, undated (Box 4, Folder 194)
- Series VI: Photographs, undated
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 195)